<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Planet HTCondor Meta Feed]]></title>
  <link href="http://htcondor.github.com/planet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://htcondor.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-06T03:07:20-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://htcondor.github.com/planet/atom.xml</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[HTCondor Project]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making Fedora a better place for Scala]]></title>
      <link href="http://chapeau.freevariable.com/2013/08/making-fedora-a-better-place-for-scala.html"/>
      <updated>2013-08-05T17:14:10Z</updated>
      <id>tag:chapeau.freevariable.com,2013://1.40</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Will Benton]]></name>
        <uri>http://willbenton.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Scala combines a lot of excellent features (functional-style pattern matching, an expressive type system, closures, etc.) with JVM compatibility and a very interesting developer ecosystem (e.g., <a href="http://akka.io">Akka</a>, <a href="http://www.playframework.com/">Play</a>, <a href="http://liftweb.net/">Lift</a>, <a href="https://github.com/rickynils/scalacheck">scalacheck</a>, and <a href="http://spark-project.org">Spark</a>, just to name a few notable projects).  Fedora has included a package for Scala itself for some time, but it doesn't include any of the ecosystem projects.  The main obstacle to having Scala ecosystem projects in Fedora is that many projects use <code>sbt</code>, the Simple Build Tool, but there is no native Fedora <code>sbt</code> package.  In this post, I'm going to discuss some of the things that make <code>sbt</code> very interesting as a build tool but challenging to package for Fedora, as well as the solutions I've come up with to these problems.  First, however, we'll discuss some background.</p>

<p>I've <a href="http://chapeau.freevariable.com/2011/07/when-software-dependency-philosophies-collide.html">noted in the past</a> that there is a big tension between the Fedora model of dependency management and the models adopted by many language-specific dependency managers.  Put simply, the Fedora model is that projects should depend upon system copies of the latest versions of libraries, which have been built with system tools, which were themselves built from pristine sources in a controlled environment.  Language-specific models, such as the ones we see with RubyGems and <code>rvm</code>; Python eggs; Java projects using Maven or Ivy; and Erlang releases (especially those managed with <code>rebar</code>), typically allow developers more flexibility to install multiple versions of libraries, fetch dependencies from canonical locations on the web or from source repositories, and rely on different versions of language environments and language runtimes.  <code>sbt</code>, which provides both build and dependency management, is no exception in this regard; in fact, it provides as much flexibility as any other language-specific build tool I've encountered.</p>

<h3>Launching</h3>

<p>You don't actually download <code>sbt</code>.  Instead, you <a href="http://www.scala-sbt.org/release/docs/Getting-Started/Setup.html">download a small, self-contained JAR file</a> that will run on any Java 1.6 JRE and includes enough of <code>sbt</code>, Apache Ivy, and the Scala standard library to fetch the whole Scala standard library and compiler, <code>sbt</code> itself, and its dependencies.  It can also fetch multiple versions of each of these.  This approach means that it's absolutely straightforward to get started using <code>sbt</code> in almost any environment with a JVM, but it conflicts with Fedora policies on bundling, single versions of libraries, and pristine sources.</p>

<p>My solution to this problem is to develop a Fedora-specific <code>sbt</code> launcher that is willing to run against system copies of <code>sbt</code> itself, the Scala compiler and libraries, and other locally-installed JAR files.</p>

<h3>Dependency management</h3>

<p><code>sbt</code> uses Apache Ivy to manage dependencies.  Fedora has <a href="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Features/Simplified_Maven_Packaging">excellent support</a> for building packages that use Maven, but Ivy is still not well-represented in Fedora.  Just as with Maven, most of the concerns that Ivy is meant to handle are either addressed by RPM itself (specifying versions of dependencies, finding transitive dependencies, etc.) or do not apply to packages that meet Fedora guidelines (e.g. running different projects against different versions of their dependencies).</p>

<p>It is possible (but clearly suboptimal) to build Ivy packages against RPM-installed dependencies by specifying an <a href="http://ant.apache.org/ivy/history/latest-milestone/concept.html#patterns">Ivy resolver pattern</a> that ignores version numbers and finds JAR artifacts <a href="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Packaging:Java#JAR_file_installation">where Fedora packages put them in the filesystem</a>, like this:</p>

<pre><code>/usr/share/java/[artifact].[ext]
</code></pre>

<p>However, <code>/usr/share/java</code> isn't set up as a proper Ivy repository; it contains no <a href="http://ant.apache.org/ivy/history/latest-milestone/terminology.html#descriptor">Ivy module descriptor files</a> (i.e., <code>ivy.xml</code> files).  This isn't a problem if we're using Ivy from Ant or standalone, but <code>sbt</code> calls out to Ivy in a way that requires module descriptors and doesn't expose the <a href="http://ant.apache.org/ivy/history/latest-milestone/settings/resolvers.html">setting to make them optional</a>.</p>

<p>I have solved this problem in two ways:  the first is a simple script that makes an ersatz Ivy repository from locally-installed packages, which can then be used by an <code>sbt</code> build.  The second is a small patch to <code>sbt</code> that exposes the Ivy setting to make module descriptor files optional.  (I use the former to build <code>sbt</code> binaries that include the latter.)</p>

<h3>Bootstrapping</h3>

<p><code>sbt</code> is used to build itself, as well as some of its dependencies.  Fedora has <a href="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Packaging:Guidelines#Exceptions">a policy for packaging projects that need to bootstrap in this way</a>, and some other build tools (like <code>rebar</code>) also depend on libraries that are built with that tool.  Because of how <code>sbt</code> uses a launcher and because of its dependency management, it is trickier to bootstrap in Fedora than other similar projects (since the initial <code>sbt</code> binary must run locally and must incorporate other Fedora-specific patches, like the module descriptor patch above and patches to work with versions of libraries that ship in Fedora).</p>

<h3>Where from here?</h3>

<p>Having <code>sbt</code> in Fedora would remove the biggest barrier to getting a lot of the Scala ecosystem in to Fedora, and <code>sbt</code> is a really interesting framework in its own right.  However, it's one of the projects where the mismatch between what Fedora requires of upstream projects and the assumptions that contemporary developers work under is particularly pronounced.  These difficulties aren't insurmountable, although I found the way that they combine and interweave somewhat daunting when I started investigating <code>sbt</code>.</p>

<p>I'm envisioning a <code>sbt</code> package for Fedora that provides the best of both worlds:  an unrestricted <code>sbt</code> environment for developers who want to use Fedora but have the flexibility to target development to other Scala versions (or to use libraries that are available in Ivy repositories but not in Fedora) and a Fedora-specific <code>sbt</code> script that builds software against system packages in a Fedora-friendly way, much like the <code>xmvn</code> and <code>mvn-rpmbuild</code> tools were for Maven.  This way, Fedora packagers would have a straightforward way to generate high-quality RPMs from Scala sources and Scala hackers who just want Fedora to meet their needs today could use the system package without restrictions (while having a path to package their projects for Fedora in the future should they choose to).</p>

<p>I welcome feedback and collaboration from Scala hackers who'd like to use Fedora (or other downstream distributions with similar packaging constraints) and from Fedora hackers who'd like to see Fedora as a better place for Scala.</p>

        

    ]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[ HTCondor 8.0.1 released! ( July 17, 2013 )]]></title>
      <link href="manual/v8.0.1/10_3Stable_Release.html"/>
      <updated>2013-07-17T05:00:00Z</updated>
      <id></id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[HTCondor Team]]></name>
        <uri>http://research.cs.wisc.edu/htcondor</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[The HTCondor team is pleased to announce the release of HTCondor 8.0.1.
This new version contains support for Debian 7 (wheezy) with standard universe, fixes in hierarchical group quotas, fixes for DAGman restarting workflows on upgrade, a fix for CCB only using the first broker even when given a list.
A complete list of bugs fixed and features can be found in the 
Version History. HTCondor 8.0.1 binaries
and source code are available from our Downloads page.
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a native Mac Installer for Bosco]]></title>
      <link href="http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com/2013/07/creating-native-mac-installer-for-bosco.html"/>
      <updated>2013-07-11T20:34:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3007054864987759910.post-9151105712164146929</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Derek Weitzel]]></name>
        <uri>http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[It has been our goal for some time to create a native installer for our supported platforms. &nbsp;This week, we created a prototype for the first of those platforms, the Mac installer.<br /><br /><h3>The PKG file</h3><div>The first step to creating the installer is the PKG file. &nbsp;I installed Bosco the usual way, using the multi-platform installer. &nbsp;Then, I looked through the Bosco files (using a find command) to locate all of the instances of hard coded paths. &nbsp;They where located in the bosco.sh, bosco_setenv, and the condor_config files. &nbsp;I modified those to use the environment variable HOME.</div><div><br /></div><div>Then I used <a href="https://developer.apple.com/downloads/index.action">PackageMaker</a> from the auxiliary&nbsp;tools for Mac package available on the Mac developer page (free registration required). &nbsp;In PackageMaker, I opened the Bosco directory in the home directory.</div><div><br /></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-4_JeICuk9Ck/Ud8VE-ZZO8I/AAAAAAAAB-s/sArZ3N51wd0/s1600/Screen+Shot+2013-07-11+at+3.26.29+PM.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="529" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-4_JeICuk9Ck/Ud8VE-ZZO8I/AAAAAAAAB-s/sArZ3N51wd0/s640/Screen+Shot+2013-07-11+at+3.26.29+PM.png" width="640" /></a></div><div>I unchecked the 'Require admin authentication' because bosco will be installed in the user's home directory. &nbsp;After these simple steps, I built the installer and tested, everything worked!</div><div><br /></div><h3>DMG File</h3><div>A DMG is a disk image that is used for software distribution. &nbsp;The first step is to create the Bosco.dmg disk image using Mac's built-in Disk Utility.</div><div><br /></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-lNMwZDZXqvQ/Ud8VvheBT-I/AAAAAAAAB-0/aTG0ulkDyNk/s1600/Screen+Shot+2013-07-11+at+3.29.30+PM.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="564" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-lNMwZDZXqvQ/Ud8VvheBT-I/AAAAAAAAB-0/aTG0ulkDyNk/s640/Screen+Shot+2013-07-11+at+3.29.30+PM.png" width="640" /></a></div><div>After mounting the DMG, I copied the Bosco installer into the image. &nbsp;Then, I ran the command:</div><div><pre class="code-java" style="background-color: whitesmoke; color: #333333; font-size: 12px; line-height: 16px; max-height: 30em; overflow: auto; padding: 0px; white-space: pre-wrap; word-wrap: normal;">bless --folder /Volumes/Bosco --openfolder /Volumes/Bosco</pre></div><div><br /></div><div>This will cause the DMG to automatically open a window when mounting it.</div><div><br /></div><h3>Where to get this</h3><div>The Bosco DMG makes it very easy to install Bosco on a Mac. &nbsp;The DMG is available on Dropbox, and will be put in production when a few more minor fixes are put in place.</div><div><br /></div><div><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/8ljehuufos3x7hf/bosco.dmg">Bosco.dmg</a></div><div><br /></div>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[ Miron Livny receives the HPDC 2013 Achievement Award ( July 10, 2013 )]]></title>
      <link href="http://www.news.wisc.edu/21969"/>
      <updated>2013-07-10T05:00:00Z</updated>
      <id></id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[HTCondor Team]]></name>
        <uri>http://research.cs.wisc.edu/htcondor</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[Miron Livny, Director of the UW-Madison Center for High Throughput Computing and founder of the HTCondor workload management system, has been honored with the 2013 High Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC) Achievement Award.
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leveraging systemd cgroup integration to provide SLAs on Fedora 18 & 19]]></title>
      <link href="http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2013/06/14/systemd-cgroup-sla/"/>
      <updated>2013-06-14T15:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2013/06/14/systemd-cgroup-sla</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Timothy St. Clair]]></name>
        <uri>http://timothysc.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Background</h2> [...]
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[ HPCwire article highlights running stochastic models on HTCondor ( June 6, 2013 )]]></title>
      <link href="http://www.hpcwire.com/hpcwire/2013-05-30/running_stochastic_models_on_htcondor.html"/>
      <updated>2013-06-06T05:00:00Z</updated>
      <id></id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[HTCondor Team]]></name>
        <uri>http://research.cs.wisc.edu/htcondor</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[An article published at HPCwire highlights research out of Brigham Young University with a goal to 
demonstrate an alternative model to High Performance Computing (HPC) for water resource stakeholders by leveraging
High Throughput Computing (HTC) with HTCondor.
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[ HTCondor 8.0.0 released! ( June 6, 2013 )]]></title>
      <link href="manual/v8.0/10_3Stable_Release.html"/>
      <updated>2013-06-06T05:00:00Z</updated>
      <id></id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[HTCondor Team]]></name>
        <uri>http://research.cs.wisc.edu/htcondor</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[The HTCondor team is pleased to announce the release of HTCondor 8.0.0.
This release is the first in the new stable series.
The major version number changed because of the project rename to HTCondor and not because of major incompatibility with the version 7.8 stable series.
This new version contains Bosco, support for EC2 Spot instances, interactive jobs, improved job sandboxing, native python API and several new tools.
A complete list of bugs fixed and features can be found in the 
Version History. HTCondor 8.0.0 binaries
and source code are available from our Downloads page.
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[ Open Science Grid releases Bosco 1.2, based on HTCondor ( June 6, 2013 )]]></title>
      <link href="http://bosco.opensciencegrid.org/2013/06/bosco-1-2-release/"/>
      <updated>2013-06-06T05:00:00Z</updated>
      <id></id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[HTCondor Team]]></name>
        <uri>http://research.cs.wisc.edu/htcondor</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[Bosco is a client for Linux and Mac operating systems for submitting jobs to 
remote batch systems without administrator assistance. It is designed
for end-users, and only requires ssh access to one or more cluster front-ends.
Target clusters can be HTCondor, LSF, PBS, SGE or SLURM managed resources.  
The new Bosco 1.2 release is much easier to install, will handle more jobs, 
will send clearer error messages, and makes it easier to specify the memory
you need inside the clusters you connect to.  
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Submitting R jobs with Bosco]]></title>
      <link href="http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com/2013/05/submitting-r-jobs-with-bosco.html"/>
      <updated>2013-05-20T14:51:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3007054864987759910.post-9067247722276578550</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Derek Weitzel]]></name>
        <uri>http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Configuring a Personal Hadoop Development Environment on Fedora 18]]></title>
      <link href="http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2013/04/22/personalhadoop/"/>
      <updated>2013-04-22T15:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2013/04/22/personalhadoop</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Timothy St. Clair]]></name>
        <uri>http://timothysc.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Background</h2> [...]
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing Spark on Fedora 18]]></title>
      <link href="http://chapeau.freevariable.com/2013/04/installing-spark-on-fedora-18.html"/>
      <updated>2013-04-11T21:37:28Z</updated>
      <id>tag:chapeau.freevariable.com,2013://1.39</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Will Benton]]></name>
        <uri>http://willbenton.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[The Spark project is an actively-developed open-source engine for data analytics on clusters using Scala, Python, or Java. It offers map, filter, and reduce operations over in-memory collections, data from local files, or data taken from HDFS, but unlike standard...]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reprocessing CMS events with Bosco]]></title>
      <link href="http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com/2013/04/reprocessing-cms-events-with-bosco.html"/>
      <updated>2013-04-02T19:38:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3007054864987759910.post-9221383956864186778</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Derek Weitzel]]></name>
        <uri>http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Impact of Negotiator Cycle Cadence on Slot Loading]]></title>
      <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/03/21/the-impact-of-negotiator-cycle-cadence-on-slot-loading/"/>
      <updated>2013-03-21T22:10:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/03/21/the-impact-of-negotiator-cycle-cadence-on-slot-loading</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
        <uri>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://research.cs.wisc.edu/htcondor/manual/v7.8/3_1Introduction.html#8555">HTCondor negotiator</a> assigns jobs (resource requests) to slots (compute resources) at regular intervals, configured by the <a href="http://research.cs.wisc.edu/htcondor/manual/v7.8/3_3Configuration.html#20544">NEGOTIATOR_INTERVAL</a> parameter.  This interval (the cycle <em>cadence</em>) has a fundamental impact on a pool <em>loading factor</em> -- the fraction of time that slots are being productively utilized. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smooth Gradients for Cubic Hermite Splines]]></title>
      <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/03/16/smooth-gradients-for-cubic-hermite-splines/"/>
      <updated>2013-03-16T14:39:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/03/16/smooth-gradients-for-cubic-hermite-splines</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
        <uri>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the advantages of cubic Hermite splines is that their interval interpolation formula is an explicit function of gradients \( m_0, m_1, ... m_{n-1} \) at knot-points: [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Examining the Modulus of Random Variables]]></title>
      <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/03/15/examining-the-modulus-of-random-variables/"/>
      <updated>2013-03-15T19:03:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/03/15/examining-the-modulus-of-random-variables</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
        <uri>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Motivation</h3> [...]
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running Quantum Espresso on the OSG]]></title>
      <link href="http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com/2013/03/running-quantum-espresso-on-osg.html"/>
      <updated>2013-03-05T18:53:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3007054864987759910.post-2337400839561942722</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Derek Weitzel]]></name>
        <uri>http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Per-Process Mount Namespaces]]></title>
      <link href="http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2013/02/22/perprocess/"/>
      <updated>2013-02-22T16:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2013/02/22/perprocess</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Timothy St. Clair]]></name>
        <uri>http://timothysc.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Background</h2> [...]
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Statistic changes in HTCondor 7.7]]></title>
      <link href="http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/2013/02/12/statistic-changes-in-htcondor-7-7/"/>
      <updated>2013-02-12T11:56:04Z</updated>
      <id>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/?p=925</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Matthew Farrellee]]></name>
        <uri>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[Notice to HTCondor 7.8 users - Statistics implemented during the 7.5 series that landed in 7.7.0 were rewritten by the time 7.8 was released. If you were using the original statistics for monitoring and/or reporting, here is a table to help you map old (left column) to new (right column). See – 7.6 -&#62; 7.8 [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=spinningmatt.wordpress.com&#038;blog=6870579&#038;post=925&#038;subd=spinningmatt&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Bosco to submit to Amazon EC2]]></title>
      <link href="http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com/2013/02/using-bosco-to-submit-to-amazon-ec2.html"/>
      <updated>2013-02-06T04:27:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3007054864987759910.post-4538100752405939638</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Derek Weitzel]]></name>
        <uri>http://derekweitzel.blogspot.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[How accounting group configuration could work with Wallaby]]></title>
      <link href="http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/2013/02/05/how-accounting-group-configuration-could-work-with-wallaby/"/>
      <updated>2013-02-05T11:46:28Z</updated>
      <id>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/?p=917</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Matthew Farrellee]]></name>
        <uri>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[Configuration of accounting groups in HTCondor is too often an expert task that requires coordination between administrators and their tools. Wallaby provides a coordination point, so long as a little convention is employed, and can provide a task specific interface to simplify configuration. Quick background, Wallaby provides semantic configuration for HTCondor. It models a pool [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=spinningmatt.wordpress.com&#038;blog=6870579&#038;post=917&#038;subd=spinningmatt&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some htcondor-wiki stats]]></title>
      <link href="http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/2013/01/29/some-htcondor-wiki-stats/"/>
      <updated>2013-01-29T11:36:06Z</updated>
      <id>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/?p=903</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Matthew Farrellee]]></name>
        <uri>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[A few years ago I discovered Web Numbr, a service that will monitor a web page for a number and graph that number over time. I installed a handful of webnumbrs to track things at HTCondor&#8217;s gittrac instance. http://webnumbr.com/search?query=condor Thing such as - Tickets resolved with no destination: tickets that don&#8217;t indicate what version they [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=spinningmatt.wordpress.com&#038;blog=6870579&#038;post=903&#038;subd=spinningmatt&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing the HTCondor-CE]]></title>
      <link href="http://osgtech.blogspot.com/2013/01/introducing-htcondor-ce.html"/>
      <updated>2013-01-28T15:33:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8803173202887660937.post-1124494645797252707</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Brian Bockelman]]></name>
        <uri>http://osgtech.blogspot.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Concurrency Limits: Group defaults]]></title>
      <link href="http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/2013/01/21/concurrency-limits-group-defaults/"/>
      <updated>2013-01-21T12:47:07Z</updated>
      <id>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/?p=895</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Matthew Farrellee]]></name>
        <uri>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[Concurrency limits allow for protecting resources by providing a way to cap the number of jobs requiring a specific resource that can run at one time. For instance, limit licenses and filer access at four regional data centers. Notice the repetition. In addition to the repetition, every license.* and filer.* must be known and recorded [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=spinningmatt.wordpress.com&#038;blog=6870579&#038;post=895&#038;subd=spinningmatt&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Your API is a feature, give it real resource management]]></title>
      <link href="http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/2013/01/14/your-api-is-a-feature-give-it-real-resource-management/"/>
      <updated>2013-01-14T12:17:29Z</updated>
      <id>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com/?p=872</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Matthew Farrellee]]></name>
        <uri>http://spinningmatt.wordpress.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[So much these days is about distributed resource management. That&#8217;s anything that can be created and destroyed in the cloud[0]. Proper management is especially important when the resource&#8217;s existence is tied to a real economy, e.g. your user&#8217;s credit card[1]. Above is a state machine required to ensure that resources created in AWS EC2 are [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=spinningmatt.wordpress.com&#038;blog=6870579&#038;post=872&#038;subd=spinningmatt&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun with ClassAds]]></title>
      <link href="http://osgtech.blogspot.com/2013/01/fun-with-classads.html"/>
      <updated>2013-01-05T22:58:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8803173202887660937.post-1674994974092153801</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Brian Bockelman]]></name>
        <uri>http://osgtech.blogspot.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Mean of the Modulus Does Not Equal the Modulus of the Mean]]></title>
      <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/01/02/the-mean-of-the-modulus-does-not-equal-the-modulus-of-the-mean/"/>
      <updated>2013-01-02T15:55:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/01/02/the-mean-of-the-modulus-does-not-equal-the-modulus-of-the-mean</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
        <uri>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been considering models for the effects of HTCondor negotiation cycle cadence on pool loading and accounting group starvation, which led me to thinking about the effects of taking the modulus of a random variable, for reasons I plan to discuss in future posts. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Demonstration of Negotiator-Side Resource Consumption]]></title>
      <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2012/12/03/a-demonstration-of-negotiator-side-resource-consumption/"/>
      <updated>2012-12-03T15:25:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2012/12/03/a-demonstration-of-negotiator-side-resource-consumption</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
        <uri>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>HTCondor supports a notion of aggregate compute resources known as partitionable slots (p-slots), which may be consumed by multiple jobs.   Historically, at most one job could be matched against such a slot in a single negotiation cycle, which limited the rate at which partitionable slot resources could be utilized.  More recently, the scheduler has been enhanced with logic to allow it to acquire multiple claims against a partitionable slot, which increases the p-slot utilization rate. However, as this potentially bypasses the negotiator's accounting of global pool resources such as accounting group quotas and concurrency limits, it places some contraints on what jobs can can safely acquire multiple claims against any particular p-slot: for example, only other jobs on the same scheduler can be considered.  Additionally, candidate job requirements must match the requirements of the job that originally matched in the negotiator.  Another significant impact is that the negotiator is still forced to match an entire p-slot, which may have a large match cost (weight): these large match costs cause <a href="https://htcondor-wiki.cs.wisc.edu/index.cgi/tktview?tn=3013">accounting difficulties</a> when submitter shares and/or group quotas drop below the cost of a slot.  This particular problem is growing steadily larger, as machines with ever-larger numbers of cores and other resources appear in HTCondor pools. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Role enforcement in Cumin]]></title>
      <link href="http://tmckayus.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/role-enforcement-in-cumin/"/>
      <updated>2012-11-12T20:20:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://tmckayus.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/role-enforcement-in-cumin</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Trevor McKay]]></name>
        <uri>http://tmckayus.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Roles in Cumin scope activities and content in the UI.  There are currently two roles defined in Cumin, <code>admin</code> and <code>user</code>.  The <code>admin</code> role is a superset of the <code>user</code> role, and every new account has the <code>user</code> role by default. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Override HTCondor installation with sudo]]></title>
      <link href="http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/condor-sudo/"/>
      <updated>2012-11-12T09:00:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/condor-sudo</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Timothy St. Clair]]></name>
        <uri>http://timothysc.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Background</h2> [...]
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Best practices for Wallaby's default group]]></title>
      <link href="http://chapeau.freevariable.com/2012/11/best-practices-for-wallabys-default-group.html"/>
      <updated>2012-11-01T20:14:53Z</updated>
      <id>tag:chapeau.freevariable.com,2012://1.38</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Will Benton]]></name>
        <uri>http://willbenton.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[Recall that Wallaby applies partial configurations to groups of nodes. Groups can be either explicit —- that is, a named subset of nodes created by the user, or special groups that are built-in to Wallaby; each node’s group memberships have...]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome To The HTCondor Project Github Site]]></title>
      <link href="http://htcondor.github.com/blog/2012/10/29/welcome-to-the-condor-project-github-site/"/>
      <updated>2012-10-29T20:15:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://htcondor.github.com/blog/2012/10/29/welcome-to-the-condor-project-github-site</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[HTCondor Team GitHub]]></name>
        <uri>http://htcondor.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the HTCondor Project GitHub website!  This site is the github web and blog presence for the HTCondor project. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Configuring high-availability Condor central managers with Wallaby]]></title>
      <link href="http://chapeau.freevariable.com/2012/10/configuring-high-availability-condor-central-managers-with-wallaby.html"/>
      <updated>2012-10-23T04:34:58Z</updated>
      <id>tag:chapeau.freevariable.com,2012://1.37</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Will Benton]]></name>
        <uri>http://willbenton.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[Rob Rati and I gave a tutorial on highly-available job queues at Condor Week this year. While it was not a Wallaby-specific tutorial, we did point out that configuring highly-available job queues is easier for users who manage and deploy...]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Cluster Suite's GUI to configure High Availability Schedulers ]]></title>
      <link href="http://rrati.github.com/blog/2012/10/18/using-cluster-suites-gui-to-configure-high-availability-schedulers/"/>
      <updated>2012-10-18T17:20:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://rrati.github.com/blog/2012/10/18/using-cluster-suites-gui-to-configure-high-availability-schedulers</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Robert Rati]]></name>
        <uri>http://rrati.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In an <a href="http://rrati.github.com/blog/2012/09/26/using-cluster-suite-to-manage-a-high-availability-scheduler/">earlier post</a> I talked about using Cluster Suite
to manage high availability schedulers and referenced the command line tools
available perform the configuration.  I'd like to focus on using the GUI that
is part of Cluster Suite to configure an HA schedd.  It's a pretty simple
process but does require you run a wallaby shell command to complete the
configuration. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Credentials in LDAP URLs when Anonymous Search is Disabled]]></title>
      <link href="http://tmckayus.github.com/blog/2012/10/10/ldap-credentials/"/>
      <updated>2012-10-10T20:55:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://tmckayus.github.com/blog/2012/10/10/ldap-credentials</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Trevor McKay]]></name>
        <uri>http://tmckayus.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cumin authenticates logins against LDAP using a two step process: [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Cluster Suite to Manage a High Availability Scheduler]]></title>
      <link href="http://rrati.github.com/blog/2012/09/26/using-cluster-suite-to-manage-a-high-availability-scheduler/"/>
      <updated>2012-09-26T19:53:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://rrati.github.com/blog/2012/09/26/using-cluster-suite-to-manage-a-high-availability-scheduler</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Robert Rati]]></name>
        <uri>http://rrati.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Condor provides simple and easy to configure HA functionality for the schedd
that relies upon shared storage (usually NFS).  The shared store is used to
store the job queue log and coordinate which node is running the schedd.  This
means that each node that can run a particular schedd not only have condor
configured but the node needs to be configured to access the shared storage. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating Cumin with LDAP for Authentication]]></title>
      <link href="http://tmckayus.github.com/blog/2012/09/24/ldap-auth/"/>
      <updated>2012-09-24T16:41:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://tmckayus.github.com/blog/2012/09/24/ldap-auth</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Trevor McKay]]></name>
        <uri>http://tmckayus.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Past versions of Cumin have relied on a local database for storing user accounts.  However, that solution adds extra maintenance for site administrators who already have or plan to have a central authentication mechanism for their users.  Consequently, development is ongoing to integrate Cumin with common central auth mechanisms.  LDAP integration is available now, with support for other technologies planned for the future. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[So What is Cumin Anyway?]]></title>
      <link href="http://tmckayus.github.com/blog/2012/09/24/new-post/"/>
      <updated>2012-09-24T16:07:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://tmckayus.github.com/blog/2012/09/24/new-post</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Trevor McKay]]></name>
        <uri>http://tmckayus.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cumin is a Python web UI developed in the Fedora community for managing Condor pools and Qpid messaging brokers.  It is packaged for Fedora but may be run from sources and would probably be easy to port to other Linux distributions (or just run Fedora on a node or two in a heterogeneous environment!)  The current development focus for Cumin is on expanding the Condor management facilities. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elastic Grid with Condor and oVirt Integration]]></title>
      <link href="http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2012/09/21/condor-n-overt/"/>
      <updated>2012-09-21T08:50:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://timothysc.github.com/blog/2012/09/21/condor-n-overt</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Timothy St. Clair]]></name>
        <uri>http://timothysc.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Background</h2> [...]
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Putting It Together]]></title>
      <link href="http://rrati.github.com/blog/2012/09/18/putting-it-together/"/>
      <updated>2012-09-18T12:59:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://rrati.github.com/blog/2012/09/18/putting-it-together</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Robert Rati]]></name>
        <uri>http://rrati.github.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Authorization for Wallaby clients]]></title>
      <link href="http://getwallaby.com/2012/09/authorization-for-wallaby-clients/"/>
      <updated>2012-09-12T22:30:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://getwallaby.com/2012/09/authorization-for-wallaby-clients</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[William Benton]]></name>
        <uri>http://getwallaby.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wallaby 0.16.0, which updates the Wallaby API version to 20101031.6, includes support for authorizing broker users with various roles that can interact with Wallaby in different ways.  This post will explain how the authorization support works and show how to get started using it.  If you just want to get started using Wallaby with authorization support as quickly as possible, skip ahead to the section titled &#8220;Getting Started&#8221; below.  Detailed information about which role is required for each Wallaby API method is <a href="http://getwallaby.com/api-roles/">available here</a>. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Authorization for Wallaby clients]]></title>
      <link href="http://chapeau.freevariable.com/2012/09/authorization-for-wallaby-clients.html"/>
      <updated>2012-09-12T22:23:18Z</updated>
      <id>tag:chapeau.freevariable.com,2012://1.36</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Will Benton]]></name>
        <uri>http://willbenton.com</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[Wallaby 0.16.0, which updates the Wallaby API version to 20101031.6, includes support for authorizing broker users with various roles that can interact with Wallaby in different ways. This post will explain how the authorization support works and show how to...]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Highly-available configuration data with Wallaby]]></title>
      <link href="http://getwallaby.com/2012/08/live-backup/"/>
      <updated>2012-08-29T14:40:00Z</updated>
      <id>http://getwallaby.com/2012/08/live-backup</id>
      <author>
        <name><![CDATA[William Benton]]></name>
        <uri>http://getwallaby.com/</uri>
      </author>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many Condor users are interested in <em>high-availability</em> (HA) services:  they don&#8217;t want their compute resources to become unavailable due to the failure of a single machine that is running an important Condor daemon.  (See <a href="http://research.cs.wisc.edu/condor/CondorWeek2012/presentations/rati-benton-condor-ha.pdf">this talk</a> that Rob Rati and I gave at Condor Week this year for a couple of solutions to HA with the Condor <code>schedd</code>.)  So it&#8217;s only natural that Condor users who are interested in configuring their pools with <a href="http://getwallaby.com">Wallaby</a> might wonder how Wallaby responds in the face of failure. [...]</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>
